Guide to the Irving S. Olds Collection of Naval and Other Historical Prints and Related Papers 1587-1960 PR 47
New-York Historical Society
Irving S. Olds collection of naval and other historical prints and related papers
1587-1960
New-York Historical Society
Olds, Irving S. (Irving Sands), 1887-1963
PR 47
23.5 Linear feet in 38 flat files and 9 boxes
The collection consists of approximately 600 engravings, etchings, lithographs, and other prints collected by lawyer and industrialist Irving S. Olds (1887-1963). The bulk of the prints portray scenes and events from the United States' colonial, Revolutionary, and early republic periods. These are primarily military in nature, most especially naval actions, with the American Revolution and the War of 1812 being particularly well-represented. Comprising the balance of the prints are portraits of naval commanders and prominent Americans (especially George Washington), views of New York City and the Hudson Valley, colonial era historical scenes, and some early maps. In addition, there are some of Olds's personal papers that relate to his collection, including his prepared remarks for lantern slide presentations of his collection in the 1950s, catalogues, a photograph album related to his wife Evelyn Foster Olds's posthumous exhibition at the Peabody Museum of her work based on images from Olds's collection, and other documents.
Related Materials Note
The bequest of Irving Olds, of which this print collection was a part, included a wide variety of documents and objects. These were distributed to various curatorial departments of N-YHS. The museum holds paintings, watercolors, furniture, and other such objects. The library holds books, broadsides, letters from Oliver Wendell Holmes, and other documents, which are cataloged in Bobcat. The largest portion of Olds's personal papers held at N-YHS are the Irving Olds papers (MS 325); these are currently being processed and cataloged and will be opened for use in May 2019.
The original Olds print collection was documented in a catalogue and two supplements; annotated versions of these are available in the N-YHS library:
Original 1952 catalogue, with supplementary pages, covering objects numbered 1-834: "American naval and other historical prints and paintings, including portraits of American naval commanders and some early views of New York." Call phrase: Print Room Reference NE215.U5 O53 1951.
Circa 1958 supplement, covering objects 835 to 943: "Additional prints, paintings, etc., which were not included in the 1952 published list of American naval and other historical prints and paintings, portraits of American naval commanders and some early views of New York: supplement." Call phrase: Print Room Reference NE215.U5 O53 1952 Suppl. 1.
1962 supplement, covering objects 944 to 1219: "Items not published in the 1952 published list and subsequent supplement of American naval and other historical prints and paintings: second supplement (June 1962)." Call phrase: Print Room Reference NE215.U5 O53 1952 Suppl. 2.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in two series, which are based on N-YHS's two sources of acquisition of the prints:
Series I. Prints & Related Papers from the Original Olds Donation
Series II. Prints from the Olds Collection Donated by White & Case
The subject content of the prints in both series is essentially identical, though Series I has many more prints. Series I also holds the documentary materials related to the Olds collection.
Access Restrictions
For more information on making arrangements to consult the collection, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Most of the collection, which comprises Series I, was bequeathed to N-YHS by Irving Olds in 1963. The balance of the collection, comprising Series II, was donated to N-YHS in May 2018 (with a final delivery of objects in April 2021) by Olds's former law firm, White & Case.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of approximately 600 engravings, etchings, lithographs, aquatints, mezzotints, woodcuts, and other prints. There are also some documentary materials related to the collection from Olds's personal papers, including catalogues, labels from the original framed print backing, and his lecture notes.
The bulk of the prints portray naval actions, especially from the American Revolution and the War of 1812, with an emphasis on dramatic battles made famous in the slogans of heroic captains. Numerous American, British, and French prints show such American triumphs as John Paul Jones's "Bon Homme Richard" attacking the British "Serapis" in 1779 ("I have not yet begun to fight"), the victory of the "Constitution" over the British "Guerriere" in 1812, the frigate "United States" capture of the British "Macedonian" in 1812, and Oliver H. Perry's victory at the Battle of Lake Erie in 1813 ("We have met the enemy and they are ours"), among many other events. Views of American defeats include the death of Captain James Lawrence when the British "Shannon" captured his "Chesapeake" in 1813 ("Don't give up the ship"). The French and Indian War is represented; the earliest naval event depicted in the collection is the British capture of Louisbourg at Cape Breton, Canada, during that war. The Tripolitan War is also well-represented, notably with references to the loss of the frigate "Philadelphia" at Tripoli.
Portraits of naval commanders are found in the collection, including William Bainbridge, Stephen Decatur, Isaac Hull, John Paul Jones (often rendered as Iohn Paul Iones), Thomas Macdonough, Robert Hopkins, and others. Some military actions other than naval are represented in prints, including Revolutionary War battles at Bunker Hill, Brooklyn, Saratoga, Yorktown, and the siege of Charleston, South Carolina; and War of 1812 incidents such as Richard Johnson's defeat of Tecumseh at Moraviantown, Andrew Jackson's victory at New Orleans, the British invasion of Washington, D.C., and the massacre of American prisoners at Dartmoor. The latest war represented is the War with Mexico with one lithograph of Taylor's victory at Buena Vista in 1847.
Many prints are views of New York City/New Amsterdam and New York waterways, such as Harlem River, New York Harbor, Hudson River, and Catterskill Falls (i.e., Kaaterskills Falls). There are a few prints of other locales, such as New Haven and Boston. There are prints of notable Americans, including George Washington and Benjamin Franklin, among others; one print of Oliver Wendell Holmes is inscribed to Olds.
There are several maps, such as a map of North and South America by Abraham Ortelius (1587); of North America by William Berry (1680); of Wight Island, England (1676?); of Virginia (late 1600s?); and two maps by Johann Baptist Homann (1724?); among others. Unusual formats for this collection include one manuscript letter from Robert Fulton to David Cooke at Pittsburgh, dated October 15, 1814 and a group portrait photograph of the U.S. Supreme Court (circa 1921).
Biographical / Historical
Lawyer, industrialist, philanthropist, and art collector Irving Sands Olds (1887-1963) was born in Erie, Pennsylvania. He received a B.A. from Yale in 1907 and an LL.B. from Harvard Law School in 1910. He spent the next year as a law clerk for U.S. Supreme Court Justice Oliver Wendell Holmes before joining the law firm of White & Case in 1911. White & Case was then a relatively new firm, having been formed in 1901 by Justin DuPratt White and George Bowen Case. Olds was made a partner in 1917. Also in 1917 he married Evelyn Foster (1889-1957) of New York.
Olds was an important player in building White & Case's banking and corporate clientele through the 1910s and into the 1920s, including Bankers Trust, J.P. Morgan & Co., and the Foundation Company. In 1926, he moved to Paris for two years to open the firm's office there. Returning to the U.S. in the late 1920s, he became deeply involved in White & Case's expanding relationship with U.S. Steel. In 1936, White & Case was selected by U.S. Steel to be its outside general counsel, and Olds was elected to the company's board of directors. In 1940, Olds accepted the position of U.S. Steel's chairman and CEO. Though the position was initially expected to be for only an interim period, Olds remained for twelve years until he retired from U.S. Steel in 1952, though still remaining on the board. Although Olds no longer practiced law during his years at U.S. Steel, he remained a partner of White & Case. After retiring from U.S. Steel, he returned to the law firm where he served on its executive committee until his death.
Olds was a supporter of educational and cultural institutions, especially in the last two decades of his life, including his alma mater, Yale, and Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, among several others. By the early 1940s, if not before, he had developed a deep interest in art and history, particularly naval history. In 1942, he curated and wrote the catalogue for the exhibition "The United States Navy, 1776 to 1815" held at the Grolier Club, which included prints of American naval engagements and American naval commanders from his and other collections. Olds amassed a collection of over 1100 prints, paintings, silhouettes, maps, broadsides, and decorative textiles related to the American Revolution, War of 1812, New York City views, and other subject matter primarily depicting scenes from the colonial and early republic years of the United States. 500 of these objects were exhibited in 1951 at U.S. Steel, and many were displayed in 1959 at the Peabody Museum. Through the 1950s, Olds made slide presentations based on his collection. He became a trustee of the New-York Historical Society and was the organization's president in 1962-63, just before his death.
Olds's collecting interest also served as an inspiration for his wife, Evelyn Foster Olds. An amateur painter, she took the themes and images she found in Olds's prints and painted them on trays and other objects. In February 1957, shortly before Evelyn's death that July, Harry Shaw Newman organized an exhibition of her work at the Old Print Shop in New York. The following year, Evelyn's work was shown at the Peabody Museum and, in cooperation with the United States National Museum and the United States Marine Corps Museum, at the Smithsonian's Arts and Industries Building.
Just a month or so before his death in March 1963, Olds made a gift of many of his prints to his law firm, White & Case. In his will, he bequeathed to New-York Historical the option to select and take whichever items it wanted from his collection. N-YHS selected several hundred items, which were distributed among the appropriate curatorial departments in the organization. This finding aid includes those objects placed with N-YHS's Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections (PPAC). In 2018, White & Case donated to N-YHS about 120 of the prints they had received from Olds, and this finding aid includes those objects as well.
(The above note was based primarily on White & Case's history published by the firm on-line at https://history.whitecase.com/white-and-case; the New York Times obituaries of Irving S. Olds and Evelyn Foster Olds; and documents in the collection.)
Lake Erie, Battle of, 1813.; Naval battles -- United States.; Naval history.; Navies -- Officers.; New York (N.Y.); United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1755-1763.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States -- History -- Tripolitan War, 1801-1805; United States -- History -- War of 1812.; Aquatints (prints); Engravings (prints); Etchings (prints); Lecture notes.; Lithographs.; Mezzotints (prints); Portraits.; Prints (visual works).; Woodcuts (prints); Bainbridge, William, 1774-1833 -- Pictorial works.; Birch, Thomas, 1779-1851; Decatur, Stephen, 1779-1820 -- Pictorial works.; Jones, John Paul, 1747-1792 -- Pictorial works.; Lawrence, James, 1781-1813 -- Pictorial works.; Perry, Oliver Hazard, 1785-1819 -- Pictorial works.; Washington, George, 1732-1799 -- Pictorial works.; Bon Homme Richard (Ship); Chesapeake (Frigate); Constitution (Frigate); Currier & Ives; Macedonian (Frigate: 1810-1828); N. Currier (Firm); Philadelphia (Frigate); Serapis (Ship); Shannon (Frigate: 1813)
- Series I. Prints & Related Papers from the Original Olds Donation, 1587-1960, undated; 17.63 Linear feet in 33 flat file folders and 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes the prints and related personal papers bequeathed by Olds to N-YHS in 1963.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized in two subseries:
  I.A. Prints and Other Documents from the Olds Collection
  I.B. Papers Related to the Collection
  - Subseries I.A. Prints and Other Documents from the Olds Collection, 1587-1921, undated; 16 Linear feet in flat files and three boxes
    This subseries includes about 460 prints primarily of naval battle actions during the War of 1812, American Revolution, French and Indian War, and Tripolitan War. Many prints also concern military themes other than naval from these wars. There are also maps, broadsides, portraits, and prints of New York and other views. An unusual item for this collection is a manuscript letter from Robert Fulton to David Cooke at Pittsburgh, dated October 15, 1814 (item 1203); in the letter Fulton discusses payment, cost and other matters concerning the building of a New Orleans steamboat, and the actions of a Mr. Latrobe.
    The earliest item is a 1587 map "Americae Sive Novi Orbis Nova Descripta" by Abraham Ortelius (item 1209); the latest item is a photograph circa 1921 of the U.S. Supreme Court (item 1213). Most of the items are undated but the bulk appear to date from the late 1700s into the 1830s or so.
    The container list consists of an item level description for every object in the subseries. For the most part, these descriptions are transcriptions from the original Olds catalogue and supplements. These original entries include some additional description based on observation during processing and data from a card catalog created by N-YHS, likely in the 1960s.
    The container list of the series is arranged primarily by the Olds catalogue number. Headings in bold lettering appear at points in the container list; these headings, many of which are subject-oriented, correspond to the section titles and supplements of the original Olds catalogue. The actual prints are not foldered or boxed in a strictly sequential order so as to accommodate size, storage, and other considerations.
    A few small round, framed portraits do not bear an Olds number; these are boxed together and are listed at the end of the container list.
    - Olds Catalogue Section A. Views of New York City (Folder -)
    - Print No. 2. Early engraving of "Nieu Amsterdam", 1690 (Folder FF-1)
      Scope and Contents Note
      by Peter Schenk. Published Amsterdam, 1690.
    - Print No. 4. Engraving: "View of Fort George with the City of New York from the S.W.", 1764 (Folder FF-1)
      Drawn by I. Carwitham. Printed for Carrington Bowles, London. Second state. Published about 1764.
    - Print No. 8. Engraving: "A South West View of the City of New York.", undated (Folder FF-1)
      A smaller version of Olds print No. 7; see Series II, W & C No. 465. Printed for Carrington Bowles, London.
    - Print No. 11. Etching by C.B.J.F. de St. Memin, entitled "View of the City and Harbour of New York...", 1796 (Folder FF-6)
      Full title: "View of the City and Harbour of New York Taken from Mount Pitt. The Seat of John R. Livingston, Esqre." First state. Issued 1796.
    - Print No. 22. French lithograph of "View Of The Tavern On The Road To King's Bridge Near Fort Washington. State of New-York.", 1825 (Folder FF-1)
      Drawn by J. Milbert. Lithographed by C. Molte. Published Paris, 1825.
    - Print No. 23. French lithograph of "Spiten Devil's Creek. State of New-York", 1825 (Folder FF-1)
      Drawn by J. Milbert. Lithographed by Melle. Formentin. Published Paris, 1825.
    - Print No. 50. Lithograph: "Washington's Entry Into New York. On The Evacuation Of The City By The British, Nov. 25th 1783.", 1857 (Folder FF-1)
      Lithographed and published by Currier & Ives. Copyrighted, 1857.
    - Print No. 56. Lithograph: "Trinity Church"., 1850 (Folder FF-1)
      From a Series of "Views of New-York". Drawn by C. Autenrieth. Lithographed by J. Bornet. Published by Henry Hoff, New York. Copyrighted 1850.
    - Olds Catalogue Section B. French and Indian War (Folder -)
    - Print No. 62. Engraving: "The Fleet commanded by Admiral Boscawen...", 1771 (Folder FF-6)
      Full title: "To the Captain other Officers & Seamen, who with a detachment of Boats from the Fleet commanded by Admiral Boscawen Burnt the Prudent & Took the Bienfaisant in Louisbourg Harbour in the morning of 26th July 1758." Painted by Richard Paton. Engraved by P.C. Canot. Published by John Boydell, London, 1771.
    - Print No. 63. English school sheet, with border of engraved scenes, 1758 (Folder FF-6)
      School sheet, with border of engraved scenes relating to the capture of the French citadel of Louisbourg by the British on July 26, 1758. Engraved by June. Published by Jos. Hawkins, London, 1758.
    - Olds Catalogue Section C. Revolutionary War (Folder -)
    - Print No. 65. Aquatint: "The Phoenix and the Rose Engaged by the Enemy's Fire Ships and Galleys on the 16 Augst. 1776.", 1778 (Folder FF-6)
      Engraved from original picture by D. Serres after sketch by Sir James Wallace. Published by J.F.W. Des Barres, London, 1778. Second state, with the Palisades.
    - Print No. 66. Engraving: "Disembarkment of the Troops at Gravesend Bay under the Command of Sir George Collier, R.N.", 1814 (Folder FF-1)
      Engraved by Baily. Published by Joyce Gold, London, 1814.
    - Print No. 67. Engraving of the engagement on Lake Champlain on October 11-13, 1776. (Folder FF-1)
      Printed for Robt. Sayer and Jno. Bennett, London, December, 23, 1776. Includes key to ships.
    - Print No. 69. Engraved map of the portion of Lake Champlain where the naval engagement of October 11-13, 1776 took place. (Folder FF-1)
      Engraved and published by William Faden. Published, London, December 3, 1776. Second state.
    - Print No. 70. Engraved map of the action off Mud Fort in the Delaware River on October 22, 1777., 1778 (Folder FF-6)
      Engraved by William Faden, London, April 30, 1778. First state.
    - Print No. 71. Lithographed map of the action off Mud Fort in the Delaware River on October 22, 1777., undated (Folder FF-1)
      Lithographed by Chillas, Girard Building, Philadelphia.
    - Print No. 73. Engraving: "Sir George Collier's victory in Penobscot Bay 1779.", 1814 (Folder FF-1)
      Engraved by Baily. Published by Joyce Gold, London, 1814
    - Print No. 74. Engraving: "The memorable Engagement of Captn. Pearson of the Serapis, with Paul Jones of the Bon Homme Richard & his Squadron, Sep. 23, 1779.", 1780 (Folder FF-6)
      Painted by Richard Paton. Engraved by Lerpiniere & Fittler. J. Boydell excudit 1781. Published by John Boydell, London, December 12, 1780.
    - Print No. 75. Scratch letter proof of the foregoing engraving of the action between the Bon Homme Richard and the Serapis (No. 74)., 1781 (Folder FF-6)
      Painted by Richard Paton. Engraved by Daniel Lerpiniere. J. Boydell excudit 1781. Published by John Boydell, London, January 1, 1781
    - Print No. 76. Engraving: "The Gallant Defence of Captn. Pearson in his Majesty's Ship Serapis, and the Countess of Scarborough, against Paul Jones's Squadron..., Inscribed by John Harris.", 1781 (Folder FF-1)
      Painted by Robert Dodd. Engraved by J. Peltro. Published by John Harris, London, December 1, 1781.
    - Print No. 77. Engraving: "Combat memorable entre le Pearson et Paul Jones doné le 22 7bre 1779…", 1781 (Folder FF-1)
      Painted by Richard Paton. Engraved by Balth Frederic Leizelt. Published at Augsbourg about 1781.
    - Print No. 78. Engraving: "Combat Mémorable donné le. 7bre. 1779, entre le Capitaine Pearson commandant le Sérapis, et Paul Jones commandant le Bon-Homme-Richard et son Escadre.", undated (Folder FF-1)
      Published by Esnauts et Rapilly, Paris.
    - Print No. 79. The Burning & Blowing Up of the Quebec Frigate, 1782 (Box 9)
      Document in frame, with center cut out and replaced with mirror. John Ensor, Script. Printed and sold at No. 4, Aldermary Church Yard, London.
    - Print No. 80A. Small French engraving of the action between the Bon Homme Richard and the Serapis., 1783 (Folder FF-1)
      One of ten small views, with a summary in French of the Treaty of Versailles, signed on September 3, 1783. Drawn, engraved and published by N. Ponce, Paris. [80A and 80B, two prints framed together.]
    - Print No. 80B. Mezzotint portrait: "John Paul Jones. Commander of a Squadron in the Service of the thirteen United States of North America 1779.", undated (Folder FF-1)
      Artist and engraver not named. [80A and 80B, two prints framed together.]
    - Print No. 82. Lithograph: "Paul Jones. Attaque une Flotte Anglaise commandeé par Pearson, revenant de la Baltique en 1793.", undated (Folder FF-6)
      Drawn and lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Printed by Lemercier. Second state. See No. 624 post for first state.
    - Print No. 83. Lithograph: "Combat engagé entre deux vaisseaux anglais et deux Frégates des Etats-Unis d'Amérique.", undated (Folder FF-6)
      Drawn and lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Published by V. Turgis, Paris.
    - Print No. 84. Lithograph: "Combat naval Episode de la guerre de l'Angleterre contre les Etats-Unis.", undated (Folder FF-6)
    - Print No. 85. Lithograph: "Episode de la Guerre de l'Indépendance.", undated (Folder FF-6)
      Drawn and lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Printed by Lemercier. Published by V. Delarue et Cie, Paris.
    - Print No. 86. Lithograph: "Épisode de la Guerre de L'Indépendence.", undated (Folder FF-6)
      Drawn and lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Lith. Coulon. Published by Victor Delarue, Paris.
    - Print No. 87. Lithograph: "Etudes de Marines par Fd. Perrot. Combat Naval Episode de la Guerre des Etats-Unis contre L'Angleterre.", undated (Folder FF-6)
      Lithographed by Ferd. Perrot. Printed by Lemercier, Benard et Cie. Published by Victor Delarue, Paris.
    - Print No. 88. Engraving: "Bon Homme Richard & Serapis. No. 2.", undated (Folder FF-1)
      Engraved by W.J. Pierce. Published by Ensign, Bridgman & Fanning, New York.
    - Print No. 92. Engraved map entitled: "A Sketch of the Operations before Charleston the Capital of South Carolina 1780." (Folder FF-2)
      Engraved by Abernethie, Charleston.
    - Print No. 93. Engraved French map of the city and harbor of Charleston, South Carolina, undated (Folder FF-2)
      French map of the city and harbor of Charleston, South Carolina, at the time of the capture of that city by the British on May 12, 1780, inscribed: "Siege de Charlestown." Artist, engraver and publisher not named.
    - Olds Catalogue Section D. Quasi-War With France (Folder -)
    - Print No. 94. Aquatint: "Constellation & L'Insurgent – The Chace.", 1799 (Folder FF-6)
      Painted, engraved & published by E. Savage. Published at Philadelphia, May 20, 1799.
    - Print No. 95. Aquatint: "Action between the Constellation and L'Insurgent – On the 9th February 1799…." (Folder FF-22)
      Painted, engraved & published by E. Savage. Published at Philadelphia, May 20, 1799. Companion to foregoing print. (Print No. 94).
    - Print No. 96. Engraving: "Truxton's Victory.", 1799 (Folder FF-2)
      Engagement between the United States Frigate Constellation.... and L'Insurgente French Frigate.... Feby. 9th. 1799." Published and Sold by E. Pember and S. Luzerder, Philadelphia. Engraving on reverse side of this print of George Washington in his last illness, attended by Doctors Craik and Brown.